Guide to the Bob Nelkin Collection of ACC-PARC Records, 1953-2000 MSS 1002
Heinz History Center
- State School and Hospital (SSH) and Interim Care Committee Records, 1972-1997; II.
  - Western State School and Hospital (WSSH), 1967-1984; 2.
    - Case Files and Notes, 1972-1976 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Letter from Elizabeth Carello to Bob Nelkin, July 11, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 15, Item 3)
        A letter from Elizabeth Carello to Bob Nelkin regarding her sister Mary. Carello objects to the consideration of her sister for transitional living.
    - Case File Records and Notes, 1941-1976 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Reports Compiled for Justice Department (Draft), 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - Memo from Bob Nelkin Regarding Justice Department Investigation, February 27, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 17, Item 1)
        A memo from Bob Nelkin to Virginia Thornburgh, Harry Goldberg, Norman Mulgrave, Jean Isherwood, Sally Hollyfield, Marlene Burda, Charles Robb, Jim O'Connor, Dan Torisky, Peter Polloni, Doug Spencer, and Ronald Archer requesting any additional documents to include in the report to the Justice Department to aid its investigation into Western State School and Hospital.
    - Reports Compiled for Justice Department, 1972-1975 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - Runaways at Western State Memo, February 27, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 18, Item 1)
        A memo from Bob Nelkin to Virginia Thornburgh, Sally Hollyfield, Harry Goldberg, Ronald Archer, and Doug Spencer listing runaways from Western State School and Hospital in July and August 1974.
      - Letter from Robert Hiltner to Bob Nelkin Regarding Food at Western State School and Hospital, January 30, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 18, Item 2)
        A letter from Robert Hiltner, superintendent of Western State School and Hospital, to Bob Nelkin addressing numerous questions raised about the quality of Dietary Services at the institution.
      - Report on Architect's Advisory Committee Meeting, January 22, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 18, Item 3)
        A report by Bob Nelkin following a meeting of the Architect's Advisory Committee listing the reasons why construction at Western State School and Hospital should stop.
      - Western State School and Hospital Parents' Group Questions, January 13, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 18, Item 4)
        A copy of questions from the Wester State School and Hospital Parents' Association following a Joint Visitation Team visit and Liaison Committee meeting. The questions examine the issues with the dietary staff and food served to residents.
      - Memo and Questions from Western State's Joint Visitation Team Visit, November 13, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 18, Item 5)
        A letter from ACC-PARC President, Virginia Thornburgh, to Robert Hiltner, including questions raised during the Joint Visitation Team's visit regarding food service at Western State School and Hospital - the visit occurred the night of resident Paul Jenkins's death.
      - Letter from Harry Goldberg to Robert Hiltner Regarding Death Records at Western State School and Hospital, January 13, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 18, Item 6)
        A letter from Harry Goldberg, president of the Western State School and Hospital Parents Group, questions Superintendent Robert Hiltner about the refusal to release records of two recent deaths at Western State.
      - Letter from Bob Nelkin to Robert Hiltner on Dietary Practices at Western State School and Hospital, January 6, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 18, Item 7)
        A letter from Bob Nelkin to Superintendent Robert Hiltner questioning the dietary practices at Western State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Jean Isherwood to Reverend Joseph Rogers, December 31, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 18, Item 8)
        A letter from Jean Isherwood to Reverend Joseph Rogers, a member of the Western State School and Hospital Board of Trustees, criticizing the lack of action taken by the staff and Board of Trustees.
      - Letter from Bob Nelkin to Robert Hiltner on "An Hour Off", December 30, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 18, Item 9)
        A letter from Bob Nelkin to Western State School and Hospital Superintendent Robert Hiltner advocating "An Hour Off" for recreation with patients for Child Care Aids at the institution.
      - Western State School and Hospital Liaison Committee Meeting Minutes, December 19, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 18, Item 10)
        Minutes from the Liaison Committee meeting called by parents of Western State School and Hospital residents as a result of concerns about insufficient, low-quality food being served to patients, leading to poor health and weight loss.
      - Letter from Ruth Scott to Gary Makuch, December 19, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 18, Item 11)
        A letter from Ruth Scott, Assistant Superintendent for Mental Retardation Services at Western State, to Gary Makuch, Special Assistant to the Commissioner of Basic Education, regarding the improvement of care at Western State School and Hospital and the ultimate goal of removing residents of state institutions to group homes.
      - Memo to Ruth Scott on Food at Western State's Pine Lodge, December 18, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 18, Item 12)
        An internal memo from Joseph McKenna to Ruth Scott on insufficient food at Pine Lodge II at Western State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Roger E. Buchanan and Marlene Burda to Donald M. Carroll Jr., December 16, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 18, Item 13)
        A letter from PARC members Roger Buchanan and Marlene Burda to the Deputy Secretary and Commissioner of Basic Education opposing the expansion of facilities at state schools and hospitals. Refers to Brown vs. Board of Education and notes that "such separate but equal facilities are not equal."
      - Letter from Roger E. Buchanan to Daniel A. Rohrbach Regarding Education at Hamburg State School and Hospital, December 16, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 18, Item 14)
        A letter from PARC member Roger E. Buchanan to Dr. Daniel Rohrbach expressing PARC's opposition to the construction of new educational facilities at Hamburg State School and Hospital, stating that such facilities would be inferior to facilities for other students.
      - Letter from Charles Peters to Harry Goldberg, December 5, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 18, Item 15)
        A letter from Charles Peters, Commissioner of Mental Retardation for the Department of Public Welfare, to Harry Goldberg, Western State School and Hospital Parents Group, regarding spoiled candy recently given to patients at Western State.
      - Letter from Harry and Alice Goldberg to Charles Peters, December 4, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 18, Item 16)
        A letter from Harry and Alice Goldberg to Commissioner of Mental Retardation Charles Peters regarding the absence of the Medical Director at Western State School and Hospital.
      - Notes on Joint Visitation Team Visit, November 13, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 18, Item 17)
        Notes from the Joint Visitation Team Visit by Harry Goldberg, Virginia Thornburgh, and Bob Nelkin related to dietary concerns at Western State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Bob Nelkin to Marjorie Matson, Tom Kerr, and Tony Wettick, November 13, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 18, Item 18)
        A letter from Bob Nelkin to the ACLU protesting the choice of Governor Milton Shapp as Civil Libertarian of the year due to his lack of action to improve the lives of the mentally disabled.
      - Memo from Charles Peters to Norman J. Taylor Regarding Staffing Issues at Western State School and Hospital, October 8, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 18, Item 19)
        A memo from Commissioner of Mental Retardation Charles Peters to Norman J. Taylor on the overcrowding and understaffing of Western State School and Hospital. Peters discusses several possible remedies for the situation.
      - Letter from Judge Maurice Cohill to Virginia Thornburgh, October 3, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 18, Item 20)
        A letter to Virginia Thornburgh from Judge Maurice Cohill approving her request to testify on the Joyce Z. case, and directing her to Joyce's attorney.
      - Letter from Virginia Thornburgh to Judge Maurice Cohill, September 30, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 18, Item 21)
        A letter from Virginia Thornburgh to Judge Maurice Cohill asking to appear as a witness in the Joyce Z. case.
      - Letter from Marlene Burda to Norman J. Taylor, October 3, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 18, Item 22)
        A letter from PARC Chairwoman Marlene Burda to Deputy Secretary of the Western Region of the Department of Public Welfare Norman Taylor. Burda suggests addressing the situation at Western State School and Hospital, including the creation of a task force to evaluate the institution.
      - Letter from Harry Goldberg to Norman Taylor, September 27, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 18, Item 23)
        A letter from Harry Goldberg, president of the Western State School and Hospital Parents Group, expressing the Parents Group's and ACC-PARC's disappointment at Norman Taylor and the Department of Public Welfare's disinterest in closing admissions to Western State School and Hospital.
      - Memo from Robert J. Hiltner to Charles Peters, September 24, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 18, Item 24)
        A memo from Robert J. Hiltner, superintendent of Western State School and Hospital, to Commissioner of Mental Retardation Charles Peters providing admissions statistics for Western State School and Hospital between September 1, 1973, and August 31, 1974.
      - Letter from Virginia Thornburgh to Judge Maurice Cohill (2), September 19, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 18, Item 25)
        A letter from Virginia Thornburgh to Judge Maurice Cohill outlining PARC's reasons for advocating for an immediate halt to admissions at Western State School and Hospital.
      - Closing of Admissions at Western State School and Hospital ACC-PARC Memo, September 17, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 18, Item 26)
        A memo to the ACC-PARC board of directors regarding the decision to advocate for closing admissions to Western State School and Hospital.
      - Closing of Admissions at Western State School and Hospital ACC-PARC Residential Committee Informational Sheet, c. September 1974 (Box 3, Folder 18, Item 27)
        An informational sheet from the ACC-PARC Residential Committee regarding the conditions at Western State School and Hospital and the need to close admissions to the institution.
      - Response from Superintendent Robert J. Hiltner to Western State School's Joint Visitation Committee, June 5, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 18, Item 28)
        A response letter from Robert J. Hiltner, Western State School and Hospital's Superintendent, to the Joint Visitation Committee regarding questions raised by the committee following their February 21, 1974 visit.
      - Threatened Work Stoppage at Western State School and Hospital Memo, July 20, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 18, Item 29)
        A memo from Charles Peters to the ACC-PARC Board of Directors, detailing the plans mobilization of alternative caregivers in case of a strike by workers at Western State School and Hospital.
      - State Schools and Hospitals and Interim Care Committee Meeting Minutes, November 28, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 18, Item 30)
        A copy of the meeting minutes for the State Schools and Hospitals Interim Care Committee. The meeting includes sections on Western State School and Hospital, Ridgeview Center, and Stillmeadow School.
      - Report on Western State School and Hospital, July 5, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 18, Item 31)
        A report on Western State School and Hospital by Bob Nelkin. Nelkin describes the conditions at the institution, the options for remedying the situation and recommends legal action as the most effective means of reform.
    - Reports: Visitation Team, 1972-1974 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - Letter from Ruth Scott to Harry Goldberg, May 21, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 19, Item 1)
        A letter from Ruth Scott, acting superintendent of Western State School and Hospital to Harry Goldberg, president of the Western State School and Hospital Parent's Group. Scott requests a revision of the 1973 unannounced visitation memo that was brought to her attention by several staff members following a visit on May 15, 1975.
      - Unannounced Visitation Memo, February 5, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 19, Item 2)
        A memo from Robert Hiltner, Western State School and Hospital Superintendent, to the administration and board of trustees. Hiltner outlines the protocol for unannounced visits by parent groups or advocacy groups like PARC and who must be present.
      - Joint Visitation Team Western State School and Hospital Questions Letter, July 2-5, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 19, Item 3)
        A letter from Joseph Howard Rodgers, minister of the Center Presbyterian Church and member of the Board of Trustees at Western State School and Hospital, to Bob Nelkin with his list of questions to be added to the report following an unannounced visit to WSSH.
      - Western State School and Hospital Visitation Team Report, March 1, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 19, Item 4)
        Notes, observations, and questions following a visit to Western State School and Hospital from the "Joint Visitation Team." The team includes representatives from ACC-PARC, the Western State School and Hospital Parents' Association, and the WSSH Board of Trustees.
    - Survey and Reports: Institutional Departments, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Reports: Security Guards, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Grievance Accident Report, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Edward B. Western State School and Hospital Grievance Information, December 17-20, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 22, Item 1)
        An informational letter on the treatment and possibility of abuse of Edward B., a resident of Western State School and Hospital. Summaries of conversations with parties involved accompanies this letter.
    - Bed Capacity Report Metrics, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Joint Visitation Task Force Visitation Notes, Drafts, and Reports, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Questions Following 1973 Visits to Western State School and Hospital, May 12, 1973 - December 3, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 24, Item 1)
        A letter from Virginia Thornburgh to superintendent of Western State School and Hospital Robert Hiltner discussing the questions and observations following the visits to the institution. Copies of the questions and observations following the May 12 and August 22, 1973 visits accompany this letter.
    - Joint Visitation Team Report and Notes, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - Joint Visitation Team Western State School and Hospital Visit Report, July 2, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 25, Item 1)
        A copy of the Joint Visitation Team's report following a visit to Western State School and Hospital. The report focuses on residents' rights and resident care.
    - Report: View of Conditions, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Physician Notes and Treatment Recommendations Regarding Quiet Rooms (Isolation), 1974 (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - Quiet Room Orders from Physicians, December 14, 1974 - February 27, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 27, Item 1)
        A copy of notes from the Western State School and Hospital nursing department, Dr. Kaplan, and Ruth L. Scott reporting patient treatment, the issues and inconsistencies with patient treatment, and the use of the "Quiet Room."
    - Joint Visitation Team Notes, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Visitation Notes, c. 1974-1976 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Visitations and Survey Team Reports and Recommendations, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Report: Temporary Admissions, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Report: Confidential Medical Task Force, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 32)
      - Task Force Report on the Medical Care at Western State School and Hospital, February 20, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 32, Item 1)
        A comprehensive report completed by a task force regarding medical care at Western State School and Hospital. This review includes interviews with staff, assessment of dietary care, emergency care, psychiatric care, and measures to improve care.
    - Report: Medical Assistance Deficiencies, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Report: Complement, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Position Classification Requests and Medication Administration Instructions, c. 1975 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Report: Otalogy Program, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Reports: ACC-PARC, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Internal Report: "Emotionally Disturbed Children's Service" Survey, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Correspondence Regarding Site Visits (Joint Visitation Team), 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 39)
      - Letter from Virginia Thornburgh to Robert Hiltner, March 23, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 39, Item 1)
        A letter from Virginia Thornburgh to Robert Hiltner, superintendent of Western State School and Hospital, responding to his March 7th letter to Charles Peters. Thornburgh thanks Hiltner for his cooperation but insists that unannounced visits must also apply to individual residents, if due to a family request.
      - Letter from Robert Hiltner to Virginia Thornburgh, April 9, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 39, Item 2)
        A letter from superintendent of Western State School and Hospital, Robert Hiltner, to Virginia Thornburgh responding to her March 23rd Letter. Hiltner states that he, the WSSH board of trustees, and the WSSH parents group believe that the current procedure for filing grievances should be followed rather than ACC-PARC visiting individual residents.
      - Letter from Bob Nelkin to Robert Hiltner on Treatment of Residents at Dining Hall, March 14, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 39, Item 3)
        A letter from Bob Nelkin to Robert Hiltner, superintendent of Western State School and Hospital. In this letter, Nelkin comments on the treatment of two residents, Tony M. and Bruce H.
      - Letter from Harry Goldberg to Dr. Ruth Scott, May 23, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 39, Item 4)
        A letter from Harry Gold, president of the Western State School and Hospital Parents Association, to Dr. Ruth Scott, acting superintendent of WSSH, regarding the rules for unannounced visits.
      - Letter from Anna Belle Calloway to Virginia Thornburgh, May 18, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 39, Item 5)
        A letter from Anna Belle Calloway to Virginia Thornburgh regarding new positions available at Western State School and Hospital and the difficulties filling them. Calloway also rejects Thornburgh's request to meet to discuss plans for WSSH dispersal.
      - Virginia Thornburgh Letter Draft to Farrell Jackson, May 8, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 39, Item 6)
        A letter from Virginia Thornburgh, president of ACC-PARC, responding to Coroner Farrell Jackson and his accusations regarding ACC-PARC and state institutions. Thornburgh discusses other issues such as Governor Shapp and his administration's work for those with intellectual and developmental disabilities, community placements, and restraints used on residents.
      - Letter from Ronald Archer to Charles Peters, January 10, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 39, Item 7)
        A letter from Ronald Archer to Charles Peters regarding the death of Roy Woods. Archer has found the responses received from Peters, Hiltner, and others unsatisfactory and requests a more in-depth investigation.
      - Western State School and Hospital Injury Notifications Letter, February 5, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 39, Item 8)
        A letter from Bob Nelkin to Dr. Ruth Scott, acting superintendent of Western State School and Hospital. Nelkin brings Dr. Scott's attention to the relevant section of the Bill of Rights for the Mentally Retarded and hopes WSSH adopts this statement as its policy.
      - Letter from Bob Nelkin to Robert Hiltner Regarding Tony M., January 10, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 39, Item 9)
        A letter from Bob Nelkin to Robert Hiltner, superintendent of Western State School and Hospital, asking about the treatment of Tony M., a resident at WSSH.
    - Correspondence Regarding Conditions and Deaths, 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 40)
      - Letter from Joy Gafforini to Senator Frank Mazzei, January 22, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 40, Item 1)
        A letter from Jay Gafforini to Senator Frank Mazzei regarding the problems at Spruce Lodge Total Care Unit at Western State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from L. Steuart Brown to Sally Hollyfield, September 23, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 40, Item 2)
        A letter from L. Steuart Brown to ACC-PARC member Sally Hollyfield asking if she can provide evidence of misuse of medical assistance funds at Western State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Virginia Thornburgh to Stanley Meyers, December 30, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 40, Item 3)
        A letter from Virginia Thornburgh to Stanley Meyers expressing her frustration at the lack of progress in getting air conditioning installed at Western State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Bob Nelkin to Robert Hiltner on Resident Weight Loss, December 31, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 40, Item 4)
        A letter from Bob Nelkin to Robert Hiltner, superintendent of Western State School and Hospital, expressing concern about reported weight loss in patients at WSSH's Pine Lodge III.
      - Letter from Farrell Jackson to Helene Wohlgemuth, November 29, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 40, Item 5)
        A letter from Washington County Coroner Farrell Jackson to Secretary of Public Welfare Helene Wohlgemuth criticizing Wohlgemuth and her staff for their approach to the problems at Western State School and Hospital and for conducting a biased investigation into the institution.
      - Memo from Robert J. Hiltner to George Lowe, August 21, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 40, Item 6)
        A memo from Western State School and Hospital Superintendent Robert Hiltner to the Administrator of the Allegheny MH/MR Program expressing support for community living efforts for residents of state schools and hospitals.
      - Letter from Robert Hiltner to Eugene and Carolyn L., February 8, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 40, Item 7)
        A letter from Robert Hiltner responding to the December 23rd letter of Eugene and Carolyn L. regarding their son, Mark, and his seizures.
    - Correspondence Regarding Staff Strike, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 41)
      - Memo from Anna Belle Calloway to Virginia Thornburgh, May 5, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 41, Item 1)
        A memo from Deputy Secretary of the Department of Public Welfare Anna Belle Calloway to Virginia Thornburgh regarding the information on an upcoming news release from the DPW. Calloway provides information about strike speculation, the outcome of the liaison meeting, and preparations made to provide service in the event of a strike.
      - Meeting Deputy Secretaries Calloway and Meyers at Western State School and Hospital Minutes, April 28, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 41, Item 2)
        A copy of minutes and notes taken by Bob Nelkin during a meeting with the Department of Public Welfare Secretaries Calloway and Meyers. The secretaries discussed terms that ended the strike at Western State School and Hospital.
    - Correspondence Regarding Requests for Conditions Reports and CPTS, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 42)
      - Statement by Western State School and Hospital Staff During Strike, April 21, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 42, Item 1)
        A statement by the staff of Western State School and Hospital regarding their working conditions. This statement cites a fear for residents and other problems caused by understaffing.
    - Correspondence Regarding Political Pressure for Admissions, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Bob Nelkin Correspondence Regarding WSSH, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 45)
      - Letter from Robert Matesic to Anna Belle Calloway, January 7, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 45, Item 1)
        A letter from ACC-PARC President Robert Matesic to Deputy Secretary of the Department of Public Welfare Anna Belle Calloway. Matesic informs Calloway of ACC-PARC's recommendations for improving the situation at Western State School and Hospital following the release of reports on incidents at the institution.